Gordimer mss., LMC 2355
Lilly Library
- Writings, (Box 4, folder 21 - Box 15, folder 80)
  - Guarding the Gates of Paradise - July's People (Box 8)
    - A Hunting Accident [short story],., July 1975; Mar. 1977 (Box 8, Folder 11)
      Published in Encounter, London, Mar. 1977 and included in A Soldier's Embrace. Original version; photocopy of final version
    - I Am Pascale [children's book]. (Box 8, Folder 12)
      Carbon typescript of text
    - The Idea of Gardening. Review of Life and Times of Michael K, by J.M. Coetzee., 1984 (Box 8, Folder 13)
      Published in The New York Times Book Review, 1984. Final version; proof, with corrections and annotations by editor Robert Silvers and Gordimer
    - In Celebration of Patrick White [article]., May 1987 (Box 8, Folder 14)
      Commissioned by Melbourne Age, Australia, May 1987, on the occasion of his 75th birthday. Final version
    - The Ingot and the Stick, the Ingot and the Gun [essay]. Published in BBC's anthology Frontiers. (Box 8, Folder 15)
      Adapted from Gold and the Gun. Draft and final[?] versions; galley proofs
    - Inkalamu's Place [short story],., Mar. 1965 (Box 8, Folder 16)
      Original and second versions
    - The Interpreters: Theme as Communication in the African Novel [article]. (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Intimate Environs [script]. (Box 8, Folder 18)
      Three draft scripts; notebook
    - An Intruder [short story],., Mar. 1965 (Box 8, Folder 19)
      Published in The New Yorker as "Out of the Walls." Original version[?], typescript
    - An Island of Rock [short story],., 1953 (Box 8, Folder 20)
      Story was bought by The New Yorker, set up in print, but never published. Story not included in any of Gordimer's story collections and was unpublished as of 1985. Thirteen typescript pages, marked by printer; galley/working proofs and annotated by Katharine S. White; three pages of notes on the working proof by White; final version
    - A Journey [short story]. Published in Playboy and included in Jump and Other Stories. (Box 8, Folder 21)
      Proof from Playboy
    - Journey to the Shore of the Dead [travel article],., Dec. 1958; 1959 (Box 8, Folder 22)
      Published in The Observer, London, 1959. Final version
    - July's People [novel]. Viking,., 1981 (Box 8, Folder 23)
      Original version, with discarded versions of pages
      - Second version; author's queries and answers from people consulted (Box 8, Folder 24)
      - Two copies of final version as given to printer (Box 8, Folder 25-26)
      - Copy edited version from Viking and response by Gordimer, with final queries and revisions (Box 8, Folder 27-29)
  - July's People (cont'd) - Jump, and Other Stories (Box 9)
    - July's People [novel] (cont'd) (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
      Two copy edited versions from J. Cape
      - Page proofs (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Research materials; notebook, which contains notes for other works, lectures, etc. (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
      - Excerpted version, published in Mother Jones? (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Address to the CNA Award dinner, Cape Town., Apr. 27, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      Original draft and final version as delivered
    - July's People [screenplay]. (Box 9, Folder 8-16)
      Rights acquired in 1984 by producer David Puttnam and director Roland Joffe. Project later given to director Randa Haines. Script rewritten by Loring Mandel in 1991. Film never realized. Nine drafts
      - Alternative versions of scenes, notes and changes (Box 9, Folder 17)
      - Mandel's screenplay, with comments by Gordimer (Box 9, Folder 18)
      - Itinerary for Haines, accounts, photographs of possible location folder 20: (Box 9, Folder 19)
      - Contracts with Warner Bros. for rights to novel and commissioning screenplay (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Jump, and Other Stories [short story collection]. Bloomsbury., 1991; Nov. 16, 1987; Dec. 28, 1989; Nov. 11, 1987; Dec. 1987-Jan. 1988; Feb. 8-14, 1989; Nov. 1987; Feb. 23-24, 1988; Dec. 1990; Feb.-Mar. 1987; Aug. 1986; Nov. 1988 (Box 9, Folder 21-22)
      Original manuscripts of: Amnesty, and one page of notes; Comrades, Nov. 16, 1987; A Find, Dec. 28, 1989; Home, Nov. 11, 1987; A Journey, Dec. 1987-Jan. 1988; Jump, Feb. 8-14, 1989; The Moment Before the Gun Went Off, Nov. 1987; My Father Leaves Home; Once Upon a Time, Feb. 23-24, 1988; Safe Houses, Dec. 1990; Some are Born to Sweet Delight; Spoils, Feb.-Mar. 1987; Teraloyna, Aug. 1986 and first revision; The Ultimate Safari, Nov. 1988; What Were You Dreaming?
      - Revised versions of the above and Keeping Fit. Arranged in published order (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Jump, and Other Stories (cont'd) - My Father Leaves Home (Box 10)
    - Jump, and Other Stories (cont'd) (Box 10, Folder 1-7)
      Final version; master pages; three sets of proofs
    - Kurt Jobst [address]., May 7, 1971; 1977 (Box 10, Folder 8)
      Given by Reinhold Cassirer at the cremation of Kurt Jobst, May 7, 1971. Final version of address; photocopy of clipping, titled: "He gave Jo'burg Some Style, A Personal Tribute by Nadine Gordimer"; photocopy of longer version used as foreword for book on Jobst's work, published 1977
    - The Land Not of Our Brothers. Review of Martyrs and Fanatics: South Africa and Human Destiny by Peter Dreyer., 1980 (Box 10, Folder 9)
      Published in New Republic, 1980. Final version
    - The Late Bourgeois World [novel]. Viking,., 1966 (Box 10, Folder 10-11)
      Photocopy of synopsis; original and final versions
    - The Late Bourgeois World [screenplay]. BBC TV program. (Box 10, Folder 12)
      Adaptation by Tristram Powell, revised and partly rewritten by Gordimer. Photocopy of script
    - Leaving School: A Bolter and the Invincible Summer [essay]. (Box 10, Folder 13)
      Published in the series "Leaving School" for London Magazine and included in The Essential Gesture: Writing, Politics and Places under title: A Bolter and the Invincible Summer.
      [See also: A South African Childhood] Original and final versions
    - A Letter from Johannesburg [article],., 1976 (Box 10, Folder 14)
      Published in The New York Review of Books and in The Observer, London, and included in The Essential Gesture: Writing, Politics and Places. Photocopy of final version for NYRB; photocopy of typed footnote; scribbled note calculating 1974 South African election results; proof from NYRB; version marked for cuts and resulting shortened version for The Observer; additions and cuts
    - Letter from South Africa [article],., 1964 (Box 10, Folder 15)
      Commissioned by a Danish paper Politiken. Final version
    - A Letter from the 153rd State [article],., 1980 (Box 10, Folder 16)
      Published in the New York Review of Books. Final version; proof from NYRB, with comments and corrections by editor Robert Silvers and Gordimer
    - The Life of the Imagination [short story],., July 1967; 1968 (Box 10, Folder 17)
      Published by The New Yorker, 1968 and included in Livingstone's Companions. Original version; final version, marked "incomplete copy"
    - Little Willie [short story]. Published in The New Yorker[?] and included in Friday's Footprint, and Other Stories. (Box 10, Folder 18)
      Final[?] version with queries and comments by editor Katharine S. White
    - Living in the Interregnum [lecture/article]., October 14, 1982; Sept. 1, 1983; Jan. 20, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 19-20)
      James Lecture, The New York Institute for the Humanities, October 14, 1982; Academic Freedom Lecture (D.C.S. Oosthuizen Memorial Lecture), Rhodes University, Sept. 1, 1983; published by New York Review of Books, Jan. 20, 1983 and included in The Essential Gesture: Writing, Politics and Places. James lecture: Original version, lacking three pages, misc. notes; second version; final version as presented, under title: Living Conditions: In the Interregnum; notes and research clippings; Five Years of Activity, by The New York Institute for the Humanities, listing Gordimer's James lecture
    - Academic Freedom lecture: Original first draft and inserts; original second draft; final version; research clippings; clipping of published lecture (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - NYRB article: Cuts and changes; galley proof, with corrections and changes by editor Robert Silvers, queries by and to Silvers; photocopy of tear sheet, marked for cuts, apparently for shortened version, Nov. 1982 (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Livingstone's Companions [short story collection]. Viking,., 1971 (Box 10, Folder 23-26)
      Photocopies, typescripts and tear sheets in preparation for publication. One version of each of the following titles, unless otherwise indicated: Abroad, two copies; Africa Emergent; The Bride of Christ; The Credibility Gap; Inkalamu's Place; An Intruder, with alternative endings; The Life of the Imagination; Livingstone's Companions, three copies; A Meeting in Space, three copies; No Place Like; Open House, three copies; Otherwise Birds Fly In; Rain Queen, three copies; A Third Presence; A Third Presence A Third Presence
      - Contents page; lists giving number of words for each story and where published previously (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - Look That's Me, with Lydia [short story],., 1980 (Box 10, Folder 28)
      Excerpted and adapted from July's People. Final version
    - Lourenco Marques: The Little Escape [travel article]. Published in Holiday magazine. (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - The Lying Days [novel]. Simon & Schuster,., 1953 (Box 10, Folder 30)
      Synopsis only
    - A Mad One [short story],., Jan. 1975 (Box 10, Folder 31)
      Published in Harper's and Queen and included in A Soldier's Embrace. Original and final versions
    - Madagascar [travel article],., 1972 (Box 10, Folder 32)
      Published in either London Magazine or Holiday. Final[?] version; incomplete version; photocopied pages with corrections in red ink and inserts suggested by Claude Wauthier; seven pages of notes on travel in Madagascar; six pages of notes, one of which pertains to A Guest of Honour
    - The Magic of the Script. Review of We Came to Town edited by Caroline Kerfoot. (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - Making Oneself Over: The Swedish Way. Review of Love's Gravity by Per Wästberg., May 1977 (Box 10, Folder 34)
      Published in The Times Literary Supplement, May 1977. Photocopy
    - Man of the Year--Nelson Mandela, statement by Nadine Gordimer. (Box 10, Folder 35)
      Requested by Robert Bernstein of Random House. Final version
    - A Meeting in Space [short story],., Feb. 1966 (Box 10, Folder 36)
      Published by The New Yorker under the title "Say Something African" and included in Livingstone's Companions. Original and final versions
    - A Memory of Richard Rive. Commissioned by The Guardian, London,., 1991 (Box 10, Folder 37)
      Final version as sent to editor
    - Merci Dieu, It Changes [article]., 1971 (Box 10, Folder 38)
      Two part travel article on Ghana and the Ivory Coast, published by The Atlantic under title "West African Diary." Original and final versions
    - Message in a Bottle [short story]. Published in The Kenyon Review and included in Not for Publication, and Other Stories. (Box 10, Folder 39)
    - The Metaphor of Exile. Review of Thoughts Abroad, poems by John Bruin (i.e. Dennis Brutus)., Jan. 1971 (Box 10, Folder 40)
      Published in South African Outlook, no. 101, Jan. 1971. Final version
    - More Than a Writer? [address]. British Council conference, Mexico City,., 1988 (Box 10, Folder 41)
      Final version as presented
    - A Morning in a Library [article]. Commissioned and published by The Times, London,., 1975 (Box 10, Folder 42)
      Final version; clipping of article, dated July 2, 1975
    - My Father Leaves Home [short story]. Published in The New Yorker and included in Jump, and Other Stories. (Box 10, Folder 43)
      Photocopy of version sent to The New Yorker editor, with comments and corrections; galley proofs with corrections by editor and Gordimer
  - My Son's Story - Nice (Box 11)
    - My Son's Story [novel]. Bloomsbury,; Farrar, Straus & Giroux,., 1990 (Box 11, Folder 1-7)
      Original version; photocopy of original, Oct. 27, 1989; revised and discarded versions, queries, research clippings; final rewrite of original, Nov. 1989; word- processed copy with corrected pages
      - Master galleys; printer's copy and revised pages (Box 11, Folder 8-12)
      - Bound uncorrected proof, Bloomsbury edition (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - Proofs and proof of jacket, Farrar, Straus & Giroux edition (Box 11, Folder 14-15)
    - The Mysterious Incest. Review of Flaws in the Glass: A Self-Portrait, by Patrick White. Published in The New York Review of Books, 1973? (Box 11, Folder 16)
      Original draft; final version; proof from NYRB, with comments by editor Robert Silvers; corrections and objections by Gordimer
    - Naipaul's Freedom. Review of In a Free State by V.S. Naipaul., Oct. 17, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 17)
      Published in The New York Times Book Review, Oct. 17, 1971. Final version; tear sheet from NYTBR
    - Native Country [short story]. Included in Not for Publication, and Other Stories. (Box 11, Folder 18)
      Original version, corrected carbon typescript
    - The Need for Something Sweet [short story],., July 1975; 1977 (Box 11, Folder 19)
      Published in The New Review, London, 1977 and included in A Soldier's Embrace. Original and two final versions
    - Neighbors and Friends [short story]. (Box 11, Folder 20)
      First version
    - New Forms of Strategy--No Change of Heart [address]. University of Cape Town Conference on Censorship,., Apr. 24, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - New Notes from the Underground. Review of Mouroir by Breyten Breytenbach., 1984 (Box 11, Folder 22)
      Published in The Atlantic, 1984. First draft; second version; final version; proof
    - The Next-to-Last Testament of Madame G. [article],., Mar.-Apr. 1971 (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - Nice [article],., 1978 (Box 11, Folder 24)
      Commissioned, but not published in GEO (American edition). Original, second, and final versions
  - No Place Like - Pula (Box 12)
    - No Place Like [short story],., June 1970 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      Published in The Southern Review and included in Livingstone's Companions. Original and final versions
    - No Place Like [short story collection]. J. Cape,., 1975 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      Bound proof
    - No Place Like Home: Johannesburg [article],., 1978 (Box 12, Folder 3-6)
      Commissioned by GEO (German edition?). Original and final versions; eight pages of notes; two notebooks; research material--clippings and notes
    - Not for Publication [short story]. Published in The Atlantic and included in Not for Publication, and Other Stories. (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Not for Publication, and Other Stories [short story collection]. Viking, 1965. (Box 12, Folder 8-12)
      Typescripts and/or carbon typescripts of: The African Magician; A Chip of Glass Ruby; A Company of Laughing Faces; Good Climate, Friendly Inhabitants; Message in a Bottle; Native Country; Neighbours and Friends (not included in published volume); Not for Publication; One Whole Year, and Even More; The Pet; Some Monday for Sure; Son-in-Law; Tenants of the Last Tree-House; Through Time and Distance; Vital Statistics; The Worst Thing of All
      - Handwritten details of story lengths and where previously published (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - A Note on Women and Literature in South Africa [address]. Given to Association of Women Publishers, Johannesburg,., May 8, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 14)
      Final version; photocopy of clipping of address
    - Notes of an Expropriator [article],., 1964 (Box 12, Folder 15)
      Published in The Times Literary Supplement. Final version
    - The Novel and the Nation [lecture],., late 50s; 1961 (Box 12, Folder 16-17)
      Presented at the University of the Witwatersrand and as the Anne Radcliffe Lecture, Harvard, etc. Published Radcliffe Quarterly, 1961. Original and final versions; final version with cuts and changes; amended version, typed for delivery; copy of Radcliffe Quarterly
    - Occasion for Loving [novel]. Viking,., 1963 (Box 12, Folder 18-24)
      Synopsis; original and final versions; draft pages
    - On and Off the Banned List [address],., 1983 (Box 12, Folder 25)
      Introduction to readings by various authors for the South African Institute of Race Relations, University of the Witwatersrand, Aug. 8, 1983. Final version; handwritten details of program
    - One Whole Year and Even More [short story],., Apr. 1963 (Box 12, Folder 26)
      Published in The Kenyon Review and included in Not for Publication, and Other Stories. Original version
    - Open House [short story],., Dec. 1966 (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - Open House [script]. Adapted for BBC television by Tristram Powell, revised and partly rewritten by Gordimer. (Box 12, Folder 28)
      Photocopy; miscellaneous annotated pages
    - Oral History [short story],., Aug. 1976; May 1977 (Box 12, Folder 29)
      Published in Harper's and Queen and Playboy, May 1977 (v.24, no.5). Included in A Soldier's Embrace. Original version; photocopy of tear sheet from Harper's and Queen?
    - Orientation--Towards What? [address]. Orientation address given to students of University of Natal,., Feb. 20, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 30)
    - Otherwise Birds Fly In [short story],., Dec. 1966 (Box 12, Folder 31)
      Included in Livingstone's Companions Original version
    - Our Violent Society, Local and Overseas Perspectives., Nov. 8, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 32)
      Introduction to a discussion, Nov. 8, 1990, Weekly Mail Book Week. Final[?] version
    - Pack Up, Black Man [article]., 1971 (Box 12, Folder 33)
      Commissioned by The New York Times, published The New York Times, New York Herald Tribune and as preface for Cosmas Desmond's The Discarded People, [1969?] Original version as rewritten for preface to The Discarded People; final version; clippings of article from NYT and NYHT.
    - The Pearl of Manet [article],., 1954/5 (Box 12, Folder 34)
      About Lotte Furstenberg-Cassirer with fictitious names substituted. Penultimate[?] version
    - Plenty [short story]. Excerpted from The Conservationist. (Box 12, Folder 35)
      Original and photocopied versions; page proofs and photocopy of page proofs
    - Policing the University: The Threat in South Africa [address]. York University upon receipt of honorary degree in., July, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 36)
      Original second draft, marked for reading; two final versions, one marked "not updated"; final version, as delivered
    - Praise [screenplay]. Adapted from short story "Not for Publication." (Box 12, Folder 37-39)
      Cast list; photocopy of annotated short story; draft scripts; rewrites
    - A Private Apprenticeship. Review of The Mortgaged Heart by Carson McCullers, edited by Margarita G. Smith. (Box 12, Folder 40)
      Published by London Magazine. Final version
    - The Problems of Apartheid [speech]. Given at symposium "Africa: The Emerging Patterns" at Georgetown University, Washington, D.C.,., March 24, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 41)
      Final version as delivered; portion of printed program
    - Problems of the Novelist in South Africa Today [speech]. (Box 12, Folder 42)
      Two photocopies of final version
    - Pula [travel article],., 1970 (Box 12, Folder 43)
      Published in London Magazine. Original version; second draft; final version, lacking a few pages; shortened final version
  - Rags and Bones - Something Out There (Box 13)
    - Rags and Bones [short story],., 1979 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      Published in Harper's Magazine, Oct. 1979 and included in Something Out There. Final version
    - Rain-Queen [short story],., Dec. 1967-Jan. 1968 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - References: The Codes of Culture [address]. Blashfield Address, American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters, and published in The New York Times Review of Books., 1989 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      Final version; two proofs from the NYTRB, with changes by editor Robert Silvers and Gordimer
    - Relevance and Commitment [address]., 1979; May 1981; 1981 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      State of Art in South Africa conference, 1979; Radcliffe Forum, Harvard 1979; Neil Gunn Fellowship address for the Scottish Arts Council, Edinburgh, May 1981; included in The Essential Gesture: Writing, Politics and Places and published as "Apprentices of Freedom" in New Society, 1981. Four versions
    - A Satisfactory Settlement [short story],., Jan. 1967 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      First draft; second version
    - Seek and Destroy [film script]. Adapted from short story "Oral History." (Box 13, Folder 6-9)
      Reduced-size photocopy of story marked for script; notebook pages; notes and trial versions of scenes; original version; two draft versions; five revised versions
    - Seven Women Artists [speech]. Given at opening of FUBA Art Gallery exhibition, Johannesburg,., Aug. 9, 1987 (Box 13, Folder 10)
      Version as delivered
    - Siblings [short story],., May 1974; 1975 (Box 13, Folder 11)
      Published in Encounter, London, 1975 and included in A Soldier's Embrace. Original version; photocopy of corrected final version; proof
    - Six Feet of the Country [short story collection]. Simon & Schuster,; Penguin,., 1956 (Box 13, Folder 12-13)
      Final versions: A Bit of Young Life; Charmed Lives; The Cicatrice; Clowns in Clover; Face From Atlantis; Happy Event; Horn of Plenty; My First Two Women; Out of Season; Six Feet of the Country; The Smell of Death and Flowers; Which New Era Would That Be?; The White Goddess and the Mealie Question (included in the U.S. edition)
    - Six Feet of the Country [film series]., May 1983; Sept. 1981 (Box 13, Folder 14-17)
      Shown Film Forum 1, New York City, May 1983 and Cape Town International Film Festival, Sept. 1981. Film Forum 1 release, Documentafilm 1 and 2 programs; contracts; writings mentioning series; press digest and review clippings
    - The Soft Voice of the Serpent, and Other Stories [short story collection]. Simon & Schuster., 1952 (Box 13, Folder 18)
      Typescripts of four stories, with minor corrections: The Catch, The Peace of Respectability, The Menace of the Years, A Watcher of the Dead; book jacket
    - A Soldier's Embrace [short story],., 1975; 1976 (Box 13, Folder 19)
      Published in Harper's and Queen, 1976 and included in A Soldier's Embrace. Original version, Jan.-Feb. 1975; second version, June 1975; photocopy of final version
    - A Soldier's Embrace [short story collection]. Viking, 1980. (Box 13, Folder 20-21)
      Final versions as published, with corrections and instructions to copy editor on title pages: For Dear Life; A Hunting Accident; A Lion on the Freeway; A Mad One; The Need for Something Sweet; Oral History; Siblings; A Soldier's Embrace; The Termitary; Time Did; Town and Country Lovers; You Name It
      - Ten pages of notes; final order of contents; photocopies of clippings used for research; photograph of Penguin book jacket; specimen of book jacket design of U.S. edition (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - Some Monday for Sure [short story]. Published in Transition and included in Not for Publication, and Other Stories. (Box 13, Folder 23)
    - Something for the Time Being [script]. Adapted for BBC television by Tristram Powell, revised and partly rewritten by Gordimer. (Box 13, Folder 24)
      Rehearsal script; list of photographs supplied by David Goldblatt
    - Something Out There [story collection]. Viking, 1983., Jan. 1982; Feb. 1981; Feb. 1980; July 1981; Feb. 1982 (Box 13, Folder 25-35)